A Guide to the Papers of Albert Erskine, 1930-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series IV: Correspondence and Personal Files
  - Correspondence- O through Q, 1937-1988 (Box-folder 41:4)
    Includes Harriet Owsley; Robert Pack; Gordon Parks; Roberta Parnell; Timothy Pember (questions about his contract and reprint of The Needle's Eye since Reynal and Hitchcock were absorbed by Harcourt and Brace (January 13, 1948); Brooks Peters; Richard Poirier; Guy Ponce de Leon; Edward Post; and Raymond Queneau.
  - Correspondence- Carlotta Monterey O'Neill letters to Saxe Commins concerning the work of Eugene O'Neill, 1933-1934, n.d., Placed in Vault with O'Neill Collection.
    Says that the "specials" arrived safely and asks him to keep 10 for them in New York and send the rest (November 4, 1933); asks him to send a copy of Ah, Wilderness to the enclosed address and tells Commins that Gene is doing a lot of work on Days Without End (November 8, 1933); but not to expect it too soon (November 11, 1933); difficulties with O'Neill's ex-wife and money (November 11, 1933); request for an extra page left in the make up of Ah Wilderness for a dedication to Nathan ([1933]); promises that Gene will sign Commin's copy of Ah, Wilderness while in New York (post October18, 1933); discusses the process of typing of Days Without End and asks that when "completed please return to us- the original with cuts and revisions- as this is Gene's working copy" ([1934]); "Gene says to set no type up on 'D.W.E.' until he arrives in New York & talks things over with Random House. - This publication will be weeks later than the production of the play - it must be.- Whether book sellers like it or not." ([1934]); and a letter explaining the circumstances of giving de Palo permission to sell one of O'Neill's scenarios for a silent movie (n.d.)
  - Correspondence- Katherine Anne Porter, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 41:5)
    Porter writes that she wishes she could contribute to The Southern Review at least four times a year but it is impossible to promise, mentions her new book of short stories published by Harcourt, Brace and Company, and discusses her story Pale Horse and Pale Rider due for the October number, "But when I tell you that it is the story of my own death and resurrection, maybe you will understand that it is not so easy to do. I am trying to remember, and then to transpose it outside of my personal experience; and what happened to me was not so important as my feeling about something that happened to some one else;" She also praises the appearance of the magazine, "The Southern Review is beautiful to look at, comfortable to hold and stimulating to read. Energy with control, speed with good direction, these seem to me its proper attributes" (August 20, 1935); and post card photograph of Katherine Anne Porter playing a piano in Paris, France (December 1935).
    When Porter and her husband return to the United States, she writes that she is "gone to the country to an inn [Water Wheel Tavern, Doylestown, Pennsylvania], and begun rounding up all those stories I have been promising myself.. ." She also describes the changes to Pale Horse, Pale Rider, "It is going to be very long, a nouvelle. I need more space here of late. There is more to tell than is possible to get into a short story. It may be as much as fifteen thousand words. All five stories will be as long as that... Now what will you do? Is that too much for your magazine? I cannot make it shorter." (October 31, 1936); She continues, "Pale Horse, Pale Rider is the most stubborn piece of work I ever attempted. I have put it aside and have written two other stories Noon Wine, which I promised long ago to Henry Schuman, and Old Mortality... It is the story of a romantic unhappy love affair, a family story which a little girl patches together for herself. When she is grown, she meets another character in the drama, a survivor who was an enemy of the principals in the story, and the girl hears another side of it, and in the end is no nearer the truth than she was before.. ." She also describes her work day and ends with "I am having a wonderful time of it, very happy" and her hopes that her story will not be too late for the next number (November 16, 1936).
    She further apologizes for her delay in sending one of her story to The Southern Review and eventually sends Old Mortality which is the first story in her upcoming book (December 3 and 15, 1936). Porter asks to read the proof of Old Mortality to correct several flaws that bother her and confesses that "The much-promised Pale Horse Pale Rider is not written yet; but I wrote three stories, sixty-two thousand words in all, in just twenty-one days. So I expect to take a long breath, and do the next two at about the same speed" (January 13, 1937). She asks for an idea about how much her story will pay because of an household emergency coming up and comments about the danger of flooding for New Orleans, "Do you suppose it is possible that nothing will ever be done to control those monstrous rivers? The Rhine, which in medieval times used regularly to over-flood the country, has been under control for hundreds of years, from source to sea... they are horrible and stupid and wasteful, our floods, it seems to me this government is positively Chinese in its disregard of human life and property... (January 28, 1937); She mentions a fellowship awarded to her by the Book-of-the-Month Club which means she does not have to be paid right away for her story (February 2, 1937).
  - Correspondence- Katherine Anne Porter, 1945-1949, 1951 (Box-folder 41:6)
    She writes concerning the good news that her French translator, Marcelle Sibon, was not killed by the Germans as she had heard and that she is translating all three of her books to be brought out in Paris during the next year. She also asks if Erskine thinks that Angel in the Forest by Marguerite Young (which she praises highly) would be a good book to translate into French. She also discusses her plan to get certain books by really good writers translated for Europe, "They deserve something better than Steinbeck and Saroyan." Her health has also improved a great deal with the use of penicillin (August 11, 1945). She replies to Erskine's account of Marguerite Young's behavior and her friendship with Sally Benson with dismay and shares a full gossipy letter about some of her social occasions in Santa Monica, California, including her dinner with the Clifford Odets, "other guests Charlie Chaplin with Oona O'Neill perfectly round with her second baby at nineteen. Theodore Dreiser and his nice wife, twenty-five years younger than he. A horrible little man who composes music for Odets' pictures... another pleasant young pair, the woman a daughter of Stelle Adler, also pregnant. The pregnant ones knitted on blue booties and blankets, Chaplin did dances to jazz mostly with his backsides, ridiculing American popular music, and God knows some of it is bad enough- but also everything else. I sat and listened to that dirty little leper insult this country and everything in it for a good while, and then took my leave before I slapped his face.. ." She also briefly mentions Richard Hale, Hart Crane, Richard Hagemann, Charlie Brackett, Harpo Marx, Billy Wilder, John O'Hara, George Haight and other people who were friends or friends of friends. She also revealed her fee of two thousand dollars for every week she works (October 16, 1945); thanks him for sending her two of Isabel Bailly's records, the only ones that she did not have and discusses other music that she loves (February 17, 1946); has sold South Hill in [Saratoga Springs?] to George Willison and has purchased her own "mountain" where she intends to build a house (April 9, 1946); discusses music, her future visit to Monroe's, George Lyne's farewell party, and her nephew, Paul (April 22, 1946); her thwarted plans for visiting with Cleanth and Tinkum Brooks and John Palmer, while in New Orleans and Sewanee, and her return by train to Santa Monica, California, while ill; She also writes in detail about her visit with William Wyler and his wife, Margaret Tallichet, where they discussed taking Old Mortality for a picture; mentions Under the Volcano; the publishing business; her flower garden; the four hundred dollar fee that Louisiana State University paid her for one night's appearance after ignoring her the two years she lived in Baton Rouge; and being comfortable with her age, "I like my age, and it's a fact you never reach the place you set out for, but continually are on the way, with all sorts of plans and unfinished business and the most endless hopes (May 18, 1947); questions about the locations of her manuscripts of which collectors are expressing interest, her confusion over the Modern Library contract for Flowering Judas and Pale Horse, Pale Rider, and her calendar full of dates for speaking engagements (March 14 and 25, 1949); and a reference to her refusal to sign an Oath of Allegiance "as instinctively as I would upchuck poison" (February 5, 1951). Folder also include photographs of Katherine Anne Porter by George Platt Lynes (n.d.) and snapshots of Porter with animals or gardening (1937-1938).
  - Correspondence- R, 1935-1962 (Box-folder 41:7)
    Includes Rose and Manson Radford (card only); Professor T.N. Ramswamy; Ayn Rand (editorial fact sheet concerning For the New Intellectual and reader's report concerning Atlas Shrugged only); John Crowe Ransom discusses the details of publishing an issue of The Kenyon Review with pieces from a joint symposium with The Southern Review, sending the work of Allen Tate, Morton D. Zabel, Joe Horrell, Thomas and John Crowe Ransom to Erskine for editing (September 3, 7, and 28, n.y.); John F. Rea; Leonard E. Read; Henri-Francois Rey; and Carl and Vivien Rowan.
  - Correspondence- S, 1936-1987 (Box-folder 41:8)
    Includes: Aline B. Saarinen; Dr. Grant Sanger, Century Association; John Sanford; Mrs. F.K. Schneider; Mark Schorer; Budd Schulberg; Frederick L. Schuman letters and his article Liberalism and Communism Reconsidered, which is very fragile (1937); Leo W. Schwarz; Robert Ian Scott; Joseph L. Segimont; Mark Sloane; Charles Smith; Daniel Smythe; [Minter?] Somerville; George Spencer; Theodore Spencer concerning opportunities at Harvard (1940); Margaret Stark; Francis Steegmuller; Roger Starr; Rafael Steinberg; Fred E. Suits; Walter Sullivan; Stanley Sultan; Paul Summers; and Peter Swiggart
  - Correspondence- William R. Satterfield, 1934-1945 (Box-folder 41:9-10)
    William R. Satterfield, personal friend who writes about his impending visit to Louisiana and enjoyment of same (November 26 and December 12, 1934); an anecdote about Huey Long in the Senate (May 23, 1935); describes a local shooting in [Memphis ?] which he visits on weekends (January 23, 1935); move to New York City (March 5, 1936; January 24, 1938); concerns about the draft (March 22, 1941); war-time assignment and military life at Fort Sill, Oklahoma, in Battery Headquarters (April 11, 22, 1942); move to Fort Bragg, North Carolina after officer school (November 28, [1942?]); service "somewhere in France" (February 11, 1944); and in Germany (May 18, 1945)
  - Correspondence- Jean Stafford, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 41:11)
    Asks for advice about her contract with Harcourt, Brace and Company, which mentions publishing Children Are Bored on Sunday ([two letters both seemingly in January 1953]); a carbon with Erskine's advice to wait to do anything until she returns from her trip to St. Thomas on February 19th (January 14, 1953); and comments about divorce, friends in common and television (August 20, 1954).
  - Correspondence- T through W, 1935-1987 (Box-folder 41:12)
    Includes Maria Louisa Taglienti; Audrey L. Taylor; Peter Taylor submits a story to The Southern Review(May 25, 1940); John B. Tigrett; R. Emmett Tyrrell, Jr.; Laurence Urdang; Horst Wagenfuhr; Daniel Walden; Armitage Watkins; Floyd C. Watkins; George Weller; Glenway Wescott (asks if it is possible to purchase reprints of his article on Katherine Anne Porter (July 7, 24, 1939); Richard Wilbur (September 9, 1987); and Bernard Wolfe (August 19, 1954 and December 12, 1961 and attached).
  - Correspondence- Allen Tate, 1936-1940, n.d. (Box-folder 41:13)
    All to do with his work for The Southern Review, including a telegram and letter about his article for The Southern Review and his request for a proof of the article to send to England for publication in November (September 11, 1936); explains his delay in sending his article by his illness and suggests that they reform the review department, "Review only the best books and merely list the bad in the back? I don't really like to be rude even to H. Mumford Jones, but how in hell can he be written about otherwise?" (June 22, 1937); notifies him that Katherine Anne [Porter] will come back home with them from Olivet, Michigan, on August 7th for a long visit at Benfolly, Clarksville, Tennessee and is willing to have Scribner's send unbound sheets for his Selected Poems if he wants to do anything with it in the Fall issue (July 30, 1937); feels unable to write any reviews about the author [John ?] Dollard (August 14 and September 24, 1937); asks Erskine if he can have the subscriber and contributor lists for The Southern Review to use to form a subscriber list for a possible publication of a "series of modern poets- The Chapel Hill Poets- six a year, three in the fall, three in the spring" (April 2, 1939); relates the results of his campaign to publicize The Southern Review in Georgia, where it was not well-known, comments about George Stevens and his statement that "A clique magazine can't hope to have circulation" and acknowledgement that Katherine Anne Porter's book had just arrived (April 10, 1939); asks if Erskine and Katherine Anne will come to see them and that Red Warren will be there for a few days (July 6, 1939); has talked to Joe Brandt, head of the Princeton University Press, about possible job openings for Erskine, in the book publishing world. Brandt asks to see some of his book-designing work and that he attend the Association of University Presses meeting; Tate also asks about the date that the forms will be locked for the Hardy issue (April 22 and August 5, 1940); suggests that Erskine contact Henry Church, the editor of the French quarterly, Mesures, if the Louisiana State University Press would be interested in helping him continue publishing the magazine in the United States (July 17, 1940); and an undated letter mentioning Randall Jarrell, [Yvor ?] Winters, [Howard?] Baker, and John Crowe Ransom.
  - Correspondence- Frank Taylor, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 41:14)
    Frank Taylor, fellow editor at Reynal & Hitchcock and Random House, whose letters are all dated after he left Random House and went to work as a producer at MGM in Hollywood. Taylor sends a telegram about his first assignment, a "boomerang-like documentary" with a Harvard background (December 4, 1948); reports on his work at MGM, with the script for Murder at Harvard being troublesome due to a writer problem but the screenplay outlines for Tender is the Night progressing very well (February 25, 1949); Erskine writes to Taylor (carbon) that he likes Ben Maddow's book, enjoyed the script for the Harvard movie that Jim Agee brought to him but recommends cutting the Prologue (April 29, 1949); long letter in which he discusses Robert Penn Warren's concern over his current novel [World Enough and Time ?], the trouble with Warren's wife, Cinina, and her alcoholism and unpleasantness, Warren's desire for Erskine to fly out and help him revise his manuscript, and Joe Beach's course at Harvard on the American novel and his desire to publish a book of poems (June 9, 1949); the completion of his picture with Richard Brooks doing the final script, a visit by Pier [Pasinetti ?], the success of Warren's film [All the King's Men], conflicting reports of Cinina Warren's health, and a letter from Malcolm about his new masterpiece (January 3, 1950); next hopes to do Rickshaw Boy in China with Ben Maddow doing the script (January 31, 1950); wants to know if Random House is interested in a book by Henry Dreyfuss on industrial design and talks about his new film based on The Case of the Journeying Boy (June 26, 1950); discusses his work with the Huntington Hartford Foundation project for artists in residence (July 11, 1950); his move to Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation, the interest of Elizabeth Wecter in Robert Penn Warren, the decision of Pier [Pasinetti] to move to Italy, inquiry about Ralph Ellison, more about the Huntington Hartford Foundation project, and the poor health of Jim Agee who worked night and day for weeks on The African Queen for a pittance (March 21, 1951)
  - Correspondence- Unidentified, 1934-1951, n.d. (Box-folder 42:1)
    Chiefly personal letters from friends, a few of which discuss The Southern Review.
  - Correspondence- Eudora Welty, 1939-1976 (Box-folder 42:2)
    Includes a detailed letter about her short story writing, "I was very glad to have an opinion on the long story- the first criticism I'd had- and to be confirmed in my present belief that it is not good because its parts are separately developed and artificially joined together, and it never was one single, whole story. I believe it is impossible for me to accomplish a long story yet- I can work so far only on scenes or certain combinations of characters or events which can be presented through the time limit & space limit of a short story, some form that does not have t be interrupted and broken up and organized according to more spacious & relaxed demands." She continues, "I've spent all day Sunday trying to pluck the short stories back out of the novelette and get them the way they belong." She also explains why she removed her short story Old Mr. Genada from her collection temporarily, due to rumors that the story was based on an actual individual living in Jackson, Mississippi (November 12, 1939).
    Other later letters discuss: interest in her publishing problems (March 27, 1959; August 5, 1965); her pleasure at the appearance of her book, including the limited edition, [Losing Battles] and concern over Marisa's health ([February 4] and March 2 and 10, April 15, 1970); the display about her book at the Mississippi Arts Festival (April 22, [1970?]); mentions receiving the MacDowell Colony medal for the year (June 29, 1970); her photograph book as her next project (October 7, 1970); encloses her letter to the editor and explains her embarrassment and outrage at the refusal of a local restaurant to serve her two college guests due to their long hair and relates their unpleasant experiences as college students at Tougaloo College, Mississippi as well (October 17, 1970); details about her photograph book (April 30, 1971); and her enjoyment of her visit to Westport, Connecticut, and the Shenandoah Valley and the Blue Ridge Mountains of Virginia (June 12, 1972).
    Welty also relates a funny anecdote about the annual Pilgrimage of the Daughters of the Confederacy to Beauvoir, the Jefferson Davis home in Biloxi, Mississippi and two requests for talks, one at the Museum of Modern Art and the other on the program of the Willa Cather Centennial (March 12, 1973); discusses her work on her collection of non-fiction and discusses Joseph Blotner's book on William Faulkner (March 30, 1974; September 29, October 18 and 29,1976); her opinion of Midnight Oil by V.S. Pritchett, "among the best autobiographical books I ever read. Honest, penetrating, selective to the purpose and beautifully written- I love his mind" and a visit from Joe Blotner (Labor Day, 1974); and her musical The Robber Bridegroom (September 29, 1976).
  - Correspondence- Eudora Welty, 1977-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 41:3)
    Includes the following topics: Welty's work on her book The Eye of the Story and her review of [The Selected Letters of William Faulkner ?] (January 25 and June 7, 1977, n.d.); her essay on Anton Chekhov and more work on The Eye of the Story (June 13, July 5 and 18, 1977); the interest of Harcourt Brace Jovanovich in publishing a book of Eudora Welty's collected stories (March 14, 1979); news of her letter from William Faulkner being sold to the University of Virginia without her knowledge and her desire to have it returned to her, which was done (December 14, 1979, and attached); description of the work of John Maxwell and Tom Dupree on a presentation of William Faulkner based on his letters, etc. (September 22, 1980); and a description of seeing Cleanth Brooks at the "Faulkner circus at Oxford" while they were both being steered from event to event in the hot sun and news that "Jim Meriwether has purchased the cemetery lot next to Faulkner's grave, for himself. (Is there annotation after death?)" ([August 7, 1987]). There are also several undated letters, basically thank you letters for the hospitality of the Erskine family.
  - Correspondence- X through Z, 1940-1961 (Box-folder 42:4)
    Includes Sukeyoshi Yamamoto; Norma Youngberg; Robert Zion; and Morton D. Zabel (The Southern Review issue on Thomas Hardy (January 9, 1940; February 29, 1940, which also mentions how good a writer Katherine Anne Porter really is; May 13, 1940; June 8, 1940; and mention of Porter going to Yaddo (May 12, 1940; May 13, June 8, 1940; July 12, 1940).
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1979, n.d. (Box-folder 42:5)
    Includes rental contract (1937); invitation to the Krewe of Proteus (1937); print of Joseph Stalin (1938); carbon copy of a letter from the faculty of Louisiana State University to Tom W. Dutton, President of the Louisiana State University Alumni Federation about regaining the confidence of the people (July 6, 1939); first day cover of George Eastman stamp (1954); Carole Lowenstein print of a T.S. Eliot quote (1979); calling card for Mrs. Frederick Worthen Bradley, Jr. (n.d.) and a limerick (n.d.).
  - New Directions and Jay Laughlin, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 42:6)
    Concerns arrangements for Erskine to take over the running of New Directions while Laughlin is in service.
  - Random House and Publishing, 1956-1991 (Box-folder 42:7)
    Chiefly articles, but including a brief history of the Villard House(1956).
  - Random House Profit and Loss Reports, ca. 1949-1988 (Box-folder 42:8)
  - Reynal and Hitchcock, [ca. 1944-1945], Proofs of Dust Jackets designed by Albert Erskine.
  - Saturday Review of Literature memoranda, 1942 (Box-folder 42:9)
  - Selective Service System, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 42:10)
  - The Southern Review, 1935-1940, 1985 (Box-folder 42:11)
  - The Southern Review, 1935 July (Box-folder 42:12)
    Copy of magazine with annotated layout notes by Paul Johnston, and three letters from Johnston to Erskine concerning the design of the magazine (June 3, July 11, and August 1, 1935).
  - Time Letter to the Editor from Albert R. Erskine, Jr., 1938-1939 (Box-folder 42:13)
    Letter which takes issue with a letter from Van Wyck Brooks to Time, recommending anti-German bonfires, with subsequent reader responses to Erskine's letter.